Guide to the Henry Bromfield Pearson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henry Bromfield Pearson papers
1802-1875
MS 389
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Chiefly letters written to Pearson by friends and relatives. Includes correspondence (1804-1821) between Pearson and his father, Eliphalet Pearson, dealing with Henry's student days at Andover, Yale, and Harvard; and letters from Pearson to his sister Margaret Blanchard.
Pearson, Henry Bromfield, 1795-1867
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Henry B. Pearson Papers consists mainly of correspondence dating from 1802 to 1875, the bulk of which was written to Henry Bromfield Pearson (1795-1867) by friends and relatives. An interesting exchange of letters between Henry and his father Eliphalet Pearson (1752-1826) deals with Henry's student days at Andover, Yale (which he entered as a member of the class of 1815 but left without receiving a degree), and Harvard and dates from 1804 to 1821. A general account of Henry's studies is given, and his financial problems and misconduct are discussed. There are also a number of letters from Henry to his sister, Margaret (Pearson) Blanchard. Approximately one hundred letters to Henry and his wife, Elizabeth McFarland, from relatives and friends dating down to the 1860s are addressed to Philadelphia, Boston, Harvard, and Skowhegan and Waterville, Maine.
There is a copy of a letter of 1802 written by Eliphalet Pearson to his sister, consoling her on the death of her daughter which is ofinterest, and a letter from Josiah Quincy (1772-1864) to Henry B. Pearson concerning Eliphalet Pearson. In addition, a set of accounts for the years 1846 to 1850 is included, as is a small amount of printed matter.
Correspondence and other materials relating to Henry Pearson and members of his family can also be found in the Bromfield Family Papers, Mss. Group No. 599, as can a genealogical chart.
This set of papers would be of value in a study of student life at Andover, Yale, and Harvard in the first two decades of the nineteenth century.
Education; Students; Pearson, Eliphalet, 1752-1826; Pearson, Henry Bromfield, 1795-1867; Quincy, Josiah, 1772-1864; Harvard University ( History); Phillips Academy; Yale University -- History; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - 1802-1804 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1805 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1809-1810 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1811 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1812 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1813 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1815-1816 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1821-1822 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1824-1829 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1830-1834 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1839-1846 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1850-1853 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1854-1855 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1856-1857 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1858 Jan-Aug (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1858 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1859 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1859 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1860 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1861 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1862 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1863-1864 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1865-1867 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 1868-1875 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Printed matter, 1840-1869, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Account book, 1846-1850 (Box 2)